Guide to the The Plan of St. Gall: production materials, 1967-1979
Department of Special Collections
The Plan of St. Gall: production materials,
1967-1979
Special Collections M0344
Horn, Walter William, 1908-
40 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Ernest Born, August 1981 and October 1985, and Lorna Price, 1984.
Biographical Note
Walter Horn, born January 18, 1908 in Waldangelloch, Germany, is a distinguished art historian specializing in medieval European art and architecture. In 1938 he began teaching at the University of California, Berkeley where he is now a professor emeritus.
Ernest Born, born in 1898 in San Francisco, CA, is a professional architect who was also professor of architecture at the University of California, Berkeley, 1953-1957. The authors previously collaborated on THE BARNS OF THE ABBY OF BEAULIEU AT ITS GRANGES OF GREAT COXWELL AND BEAULIEU-ST. LEONARD, University of California Press, 1965.
Scope and Content
The collection of production materials for The Plan of St. Gall is composed of materials formerly in the possession of the donors, Mr. and Mrs. Ernest Born and Lorna Price. It is composed of A variety of materials representing numerous stages in the production of the three volume work. A great deal of the material is undated. Those which are dated range from 1967, during the early phases of the project, to just prior to publication at the end of 1979. They include research correspondence; corrected typescript; galley, page and reproduction proofs; illustrations, including original drawings, photographic reproductions and negatives, pasteups, cropping and placement instructions, and scales; design and production materials, including layouts, press sheets, studies and proofs for the binding calligraphy and endpapers, and minor miscellaneous materials; publicity and advertising materials; and a certificate of commendation from the University of California Press.
The collection focuses not on the research which was undertaken to produce the intellectual content of the work but emphasizes the meticulous and exacting process of producing the volumes which present the results of research. Development of the book design may be traced from the designers blueprint schematic layouts, through the interconnected states of planning layouts, page designs and proofs, to the final, unbound signatures. Additional elements of the book arts are represented by the studies and proofs for the binding calligraphy and endpapers. The collection materials also suggest something of the relationships between author, editor, and printer and the interplay required of their respective functions. Even post-press stages are represented by the examples of publicity and advertising and the certificate of commendation.
Some development of text may be traced through the stages of typescript, galley, page and, finally, reproduction proofs. There are, indeed, many relatively minor but interesting changes which may be followed. Utilizing the finished volumes as an index, the development of an individual page may be traced, problem areas identified, and the judgment of the designer or author observed. It is the design material, however, which provides the more complete illustration of the stages and states involved in a project of this kind and which is the principal strength of the collection.
Unfortunately, the collection is not complete. Research and correspondence are quite minor. Corrected typescript and proofs are present for each volume, some in several states, but the first state manuscript which was heavily rewritten, is not included. The graphic and design materials are also incomplete, since every drawing or pasteup represented in the finished work is present. The materials included, however, should be considered of especial interest.
The page layouts in their several forms illustrate Born's concern for and involvement with the most minute details of the design. They are typically covered with annotations and directions for the printer. Handwritten notes are often attached to the individual pages. The layouts may, indeed, have been the principal means of editing during the latter states of the project.
Born used drawings, pasteups, and a few photo reproductions in illustrating St. Gall. His original drawings are fine examples of his considerable and acknowledged skill as a graphic artist. His pasteups are fascinating examples of the complexity and finesse which can be required in printing illustrations. Most are ingenious composites of several media where details are often highlighted or altered by layers of transparent overlays.
The miscellaneous series, though small, does contain advertising and publicity materials as well as a certificate of commendation printed by Lawton Kennedy and presented to Czeslaw Jan Grycz from the Press.
ORGANIZATION OF THE RECORDS
The collection is organized into the following series and subseries; research correspondence; text, consisting of typescript and proofs; illustrations for the text, including drawings, photographic reproductions and negatives, pasteups, crop and placement instructions, and graphic scales; design and production materials, containing layouts in several stages and formats, binding calligraphy studies and proofs, and endpaper studies and proofs; and a small group of miscellaneous items including advertising and publicity materials and a certificate of commendation.
Materials are, where appropriate, arranged numerically by page or figure number within their series and subseries reflecting their location in the finished volumes. When materials exist in more than one state they are either grouped within that state and labeled, as the galley proofs have been labeled, or they are interfield by page number with the earliest state first. The page proofs and page designs have been arranged in this manner. Because the materials in the collection vary so greatly in size items in the same series may be filed in more than one location. The outline of the collection contents should ease any initial confusion which this may cause. The finished volumes themselves act as an index for accessing the collection and should be used to locate specific pages and/or illustrations.
Series Description
- Series I: RESEARCH CORRESPONDENCE, 1972-1979 (Box 1)
  Despite the many years of research devoted to this project research and correspondence form an almost insignificant part of the collection. The notes and research material included are really quite minor. The correspondence, while revealing of working relationships, is relatively small when considering the great length of time involved in the work. The nature of the collaboration between the authors and their editor seems to have eliminated the need for much of the conventional correspondence expected with such a project. All three worked very closely together with almost daily interaction, either in person or by telephone. Walter Horn and Lorna Price did, in fact, share office space for some time in the art history department of U.C. Berkeley. And much of the later collaborative work between Price and Born on design took place in Born's San Francisco home/studio. Brief notes from all three individuals frequently appear on proofs and layouts which were apparently circulated among the principals. Working meetings between Horn, Born and Price were apparently held almost weekly and were a major means of communication, composition and revision. Communication was, thus, to a great extent verbal and, therefore, undocumented. Correspondence in this series includes material by Born, Clowes, Grycz, Norma Farquhar, Horn, Price, and the advertising firm of Wilton, Coombs and Colnett.
- Series II: TEXT 1972-1979.
  This series contains material related to the development of St. Gall' s textual content. It includes, therefore, corrected typescript and four types of proofs. Since the heavily rewritten first manuscript has unfortunately been lost the genesis of the text is not to be found in this collection. Despite these deficiencies, however, some evolution in the text can be followed via the typescript and the various proof states. Most of the proofs are edited. Many are, in fact, replete with messages, notations and corrections, some of which are corrections of content. It is within this limited context that the reader may observe an evolution of the text.
  - A. Corrected Typescript (Box (Boxes 1-4)
    Typescript for volume I includes several pages of text, galley corrections and footnotes and most of the captions; for volume II, most of the text, some galley corrections and footnotes and most of the captions; for volume III, most of the text for its various parts as well as three states of appendix I and two states of appendix II.
  - B. Proofs (Box (Boxes 4-12, OS 1)
    Galley proofs for volume I include states from 1970, 1971, and 1973/75. Galleys for volume II include states from 1970/71 and 1973. Volume III is represented by single state galleys for appendix I, the glossary, the bibliography, and the chronology and range from 1975 to 1979. Galleys are limited for volume III since the manuscript for this volume was set directly in page proof.
    Page proofs for volume I, largely undated, range from 1974 to 1978. The bulk of the proofs probably date from 1977. Volume II page proofs are also essentially undated but since they incorporate captions can be assumed to be later state proofs. Volume III page proofs range from 1973 but significant numbers also bear stamped dates from 1974 and 1979.
    The reproduction proofs for all three volumes are undated but are among the final stages of the printing process. In contrast to the earlier proofs the reproduction proofs are largely unedited.
    Possible final state (?) proofs include a small number of untrimmed page proofs, several uncut and incomplete signatures, and a small group of what appear to be cut signatures ready for binding. All are undated, uncorrected, and obviously from the latter stages of the project.
- Series III: ILLUSTRATIONS FOR TEXT, 1975-1979.
  The collection contains much of the material utilized for illustrations, including many of Ernest Born's original drawings; photographic reproductions, negatives and color plates; cropping and placement instructions; graphic scales; and Born's ingenious pasteups composed of several different materials. Most of the illustrations are in their final state and camera ready. their development cannot, therefore, in most cases be traced. They are, however, superb examples of architectural illustration and attest to Born's considerable gifts as an artist and illustrator. Since they range radically in size, illustration material occurs in three different arrangements depending upon the size of the item. Dates which may be assumed to be completion dates are usually stamped on the material and range from 1974 to 1979.
  - A. Drawings (Box (Boxes 13-14, OS 2-3)
    Drawings, either in pen and ink or pencil, are included for all three volumes. They occur in two different size ranges and utilize a number of different grounds.
  - B. Photographic Reproductions (Box (Boxes 7-12, 15, unboxed roll)
    Reproductions include both photographs and contact prints from all three volumes. They occur in four different size ranges and include the oversize reproduction of the Plan itself.
  - C. Negatives and Color Plates (Box (Boxes 7, 12, 15)
    This is a rather small subseries which includes negatives and color field plates for five different illustrations found in volume I. They occur in three different size ranges.
  - D. Pasteups (Box (Boxes 15-18, OS 4-5)
    Pasteups occur in two size ranges and include illustrations from all three volumes. They allowed Born to repeat images with perfect consistancy while shifting focus to sections of or details in the image. They usually consist of contact prints affixed to a ground with one or more transparent plastic overlays hinged with tape.
  - E. Cropping and Placement Instructions for Detailed Segments (Box 12)
    This is a minor subseries which includes a small number of detail segments from volume III, appendix I, and contain Born's comments and instructions concerning their placement on the page.
  - F. Graphic Scales (Box (Boxes 7, 10)
    This is another minor subseries which contains material used for supporting the illustrations in the publication. Included is a set of graduated scales used by Born as an aid in regulating the relative size of an illustration on a page. The scales could be applied to any illustration and Born made many copies of each size. They are often discussed by Born in his concern for the balance and proportions of a particular page design. Also included is another group of scales, larger in size than the first, which are labeled for specific illustrations.
- Series IV: DESIGN AND PRODUCTION MATERIALS, 1968-1979.
  The primary strength of the collection lies in the illustration which it provides of the many phases involved in the design and printing of a great book. These design materials consist of layouts, including two planning layouts for paging, page designs, proofs, and a few relatively minor but interesting materials utilized in the design and printing process; and studies and proofs for the binding calligraphy and endpapers. Most of the layouts provide important instructions and/or comments for the typesetter, printer and proofreaders and provided opportunities for additional editing when necessary.
  - A. Layouts (Box (Boxes 7, 19-32, OS)
    The schematic layouts range in date from 1968 to 1973. They are the earliest design materials in the collection and were produced by Born as an initial means of testing the subtle balances and arrangements in the designs of his pages. Born began producing them before the typescript was even set in galley and most carry one or more revision dates.
    Of the two planning layouts for paging the first is rough and preliminary. It is a working tool, containing numerous revisions and alterations and bears the stamped dates of both 1974 and 1975. Both layouts were utilized as a means of visualizing the work as a whole, page by page. The second, though undated, is most likely later than the first and not a working copy. It is a finished version which was probably intended for an editorial or publishing committee presentation.
    The page designs, pasteups utilizing cannibalized galleys, proofs, typescript, manuscript, and occasionally original drawing, are especially interesting as examples of the meticulous care and detail invested in the work. It was at this stage that true mock-ups of the individual pages were produced. In this form the design was further refined, spacing checked and rechecked, and artwork finally lifted to place on the page. These may also be the dummys mentioned in the editor's inventory of bookmaking artifacts. The collection contains a near complete representation for all three volumes. Many appear in two or more states. Most states have also been further revised and annotated. Volume I designs date from both 1974 and 1976. Volume II carries dates from 1975, 1976 and 1978. A xerox set of volume II is dated in both 1974 and 1975. Volume III bears dates from 1973, 1974, 1978 and 1979. These designs were sent to Clowes for further revision of the typography. They provide what are, perhaps, the most visual and certainly the most vivid illustrations in the collection of page development as a design problem.
    The proofs include proof tests for headings, display, paging, and paper makeup. The small group of minor materials include a small number of notes concerning production and layout, Lorna Price's inventory of bookmaking artifacts, and tally sheets of page makeup adjustments.
  - B. Binding Calligraphy Studies and Proofs (Box 31)
    Included in this small subseries are Born's studies for the style and placement of lettering found on the spines of the volumes as well as final proofs of his calligraphy.
  - C. Endpaper Studies and Proofs (Box (OS 1)
    Included in this minor subseries are Born's studies for St. Gall' s endpapers. Each volume presents the design in a different color. Proof sheets are included for each of the three colors.
- Series V: MISCELLANEOUS, 1978.
  Those miscellaneous items in the collection include publicity and advertising materials and a certificate of commendation from the U.C. Press.
  - A. Publicity and Advertising (Box (Boxes 7, 12, OS 1)
    Materials include typescript for the promotional prospectus, the prospectus itself, and proof sheets for an announcement of an exhibit illustrating the project which was mounted in 1979. The prospectus is highly recommended as a source of additional, detailed information on the printing processes utilized in the work and as a useful introduction to the volumes for those unfamiliar with the authors and the Plan of St. Gall project.
  - B. Certificate of Commendation (Box 12)
    Consists of a certificate of commendation printed by Lawton Kennedy and presented to Czeslaw Jan Grycz from the University of California Press upon the completion of the St. Gall project.
The Plan of St. Gall
THE PLAN
On Christmas Day 1979 the University of California Press published Walter Horn and Ernest Born's The Plan of St. Gall after a fifteen year gestational period. The three volume work, subtitled a study of the architecture and economy of, and life in a paradigmatic Carolingian monastery, is based on the early ninth century parchment known as the Plan of St. Gall, one of the great cultural and historical documents of Western civilization. Possibly the sole surviving architectural drawing between late antiquity and the Gothic period, it was to influence both secular and monastic design and construction for centuries. The Plan itself is a ninth century schematic groundplan, traced in red ink on a 30.5" × 44" sheet of vellum, delineating an ideal Carolingian monastic complex. Inscriptions in brown ink identify the functions of each building in the drawing. A dedicatory inscription informs the reader that the Plan was drawn at the request of Abbot Gozbert, abbot of the monastery of St. Gall from 816 to 836. A national treasure, the Plan now rests in the Stiftsbibliothek, St. Gall, Switzerland.
The product of the intellectual elite of the Age of Charlemagne and part of a general movement of monastic reform in the ninth century, the Plan depicts as a groundplan an ideal, autonomous monastic community. Most likely a ninth century copy of a document produced by the two synods held at Aachen in 816 and 817, it was not intended to represent a single, specific monastic complex. Rather, the Plan was meant to act as a prototypic model and planning guide. Adaptations for individual site characteristics were undoubtedly necessary and anticipated by the designers. It almost certainly provided the form for the ninth century reconstruction of the abbey of St. Gall in Switzerland in whose library the original plan now rests.
The Plan was first and foremost the materialization of a utopian vision of an efficient, liturgically sound, productive, and self-perpetuating community of individuals. It was, according to the authors, a fully transferable building plan, intended to not only standardize monastic architecture and community planning but to also participate in the general reform of the Benedictine Rule encouraged by Charlemagne. Horn and Born maintain that the Plan provides a remarkable illustration of the drive toward a linguistic, religious, and political unity sought in the Carolingian age. They summerize the artifact by stating that it gathers, as in a lens, an image of the whole of Carolingian life.
The Plan has itself been the subject of some controversy since it's rediscovery by Henricus Canisius in 1604. In 1844 the first published interpretation of the buildings was attempted in a monograph by Ferdinand Keller. Keller's study and subsequent ones by Robert Willis (1848), Albert Lenoir (1852), and Leclerq (1924) were neither free of error or omissions, but represent the beginning of a profound and lasting fascination which the Plan has held for medievalists in many disciplines.
THE WORK
The authors subjected both the Plan itself and contemporary evidence to intense examination and analysis, focusing not only on the possible physical natures of the structures delineated by the groundplan, but also on their probable functions and underlying cultural, religious, and sociological bases. Their reconstruction of the complex is thus both intellectual and visual, philosophical and physical.
Their work presents not only a possible reconstruction of the monastic structures, but also of the monastic economy -- the daily, indeed hourly, activities which took place within those structures. Proportional principles manifested in the St. Gall plan are emphasized by the inclusion of an appendix by A. Hunter Dupree, The Significance of the Plan of St. Gall to the History of Measurement. The authors also include a section devoted to three important translations. The first is a translation and paleographic analysis by Bernard Bischoff of the explanatory inscriptions on the Plan itself, calligraphic inscriptions which reveal the probable scriptorial origin of the ninth century copy. The second and third are translations by Charles W. Jones of two monastic management manuals: the brief Constitution of Ansegis, Abbot of Fontanella (823-833); and the Consuetudines Corbeienses by Abbot Adalhard of Corbie (753-826), a treatise on administration so learned and profound that it's counterparts in the secular world would Have been found only in the highest levels of government at the Imperial court.
THE AUTHORS
Both the authors and editor came to the St. Gall project with backgrounds and experience which permitted a successful collaboration. Walter Horn, (1908-), was born in Waldangelloch, Germany and studied art history at the universities of Heidelberg, Berlin, and Hamburg between 1926 and 1933. Between 1934 and 1937 he was a postdoctoral research associate at the German Institute of Art in Florence. A student of Erwin Panofsky, Horn has described his own scholarly life as a long preoccupation with processes of cultural transformation deriving from interaction of classical concepts with northern elements in medieval art. Leaving Germany in 1938, he was invited to teach at the University of California, Berkeley. He remained at Berkeley as professor of art history until 1974, taking time out to serve in the U.S. Army from 1944-1946. The recipient of numerous honors and awards, he has continued to retain his connection with the university as professor emeritus.